<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Observations on the letter written by the Duke of Buckingham to Sir Thomas Osborn, upon the reading of a book called The present interest of England stated written in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2374</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16987818</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16987818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105626</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105626)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1096:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Observations on the letter written by the Duke of Buckingham to Sir Thomas Osborn, upon the reading of a book called The present interest of England stated written in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697.</author>
                  <author>Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680.</author>
                  <author>Leeds, Thomas Osborne, Duke of, 1631-1712.</author>
                  <author>Lisola, François Paul, baron de, 1613-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The worlds mistake in Oliver Cromwel, or, A short political discourse, shewing, that Cromwell's maladministration, (during his four years and nine months pretended protectorship) laid the foundation fo our present condition, in the decay of trade" (p. [27]-54) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>"April 17. anno 1669 ..." (p. 24-26) is an opinion by Denzil Holles concerning the case of Sir Francis Toppe.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Slingsby Bethel. cf. BM; NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Also attributed by Wing to François Paul de Lisola.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bethel, Slingsby, 1617-1697. --  Present interest of England stated.</term>
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1628-1687. --  Letter to Sir Thomas Osborn.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105626:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>OBSERVATIONS ON THE LETTER Written by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> TO Sir <hi>THOMAS OSBORN,</hi> Upon the Reading of a Book, CALLED, The Preſent Intereſt OF ENGLAND STATED.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Written in a Letter to a Friend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105626:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105626:2"/>
                  <head>Obſervations on the Letter Written by the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> to Sir <hi>Thomas Osborn,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SO ſoon as ſome indiſpenſible Occaſions would permit, I did at your inſtance, ſtrictly peruſe the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> called, <hi>The Preſent Intereſt of</hi> England <hi>Stated;</hi> As alſo, the Letter directed to Sir <hi>Thomas Osborn</hi> in anſwer to it, and at your requeſt, ſhall now give you my Senſe of <hi>both.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I find no Cauſe, by the Scope of the <hi>Letter,</hi> to believe otherwiſe of the <hi>Author,</hi> than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Profeſſions, that he really deſigns the <hi>Honour, Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> of this <hi>Nation.</hi> An Honeſt and Honourable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, the perfect diſcovery whereof, I wiſh may be purſued by Men of leaſure, and put in practice by thoſe of <hi>Power.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I underſtand the <hi>Letter</hi> to agree fully with the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> in all its Maxims relating to our <hi>Domeſtick Intereſt,</hi> not differing neither from our <hi>Foreign</hi> in any thing, ſave what relates to <hi>Holland,</hi> and therein likewiſe, not in <hi>all,</hi> but only in <hi>ſome</hi> Particulars, but in <hi>ſeveral</hi> of them; I obſerve alſo the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> to be by the <hi>Letter</hi> exceedingly miſtaken; for whereas <hi>it</hi> renders him ſo <hi>Byaſſed</hi> with <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105626:3"/>to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as makes him overlook the uſefulneſs of <hi>Foreign Alliances.</hi> I cannot judge, but he grounds all he writes concerning <hi>Holland,</hi> upon the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> inſomuch as it ſeems ſtrange to me, how a Perſon of that Candor and Ingenuity, as the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Letter</hi> is, ſhould be ſo far miſtaken, as to inſinuate to the World, that the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> he anſwereth, pleadeth</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>For allowing all the Injuries and Wrongs done by the</hi> Hollanders <hi>to this Nation,</hi> (Page 5.)</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>For ſtudying of their Intereſts, and loving of them; becauſe they are Traders, though by being ſo, they take our Trade from us,</hi> (Page 5, 6.)</p>
                  <p>And Thirdly, <hi>That their Parſimony is no good Reaſon for diſlike of them,</hi> (Page 6.) As if all theſe were Arguments made uſe of by expreſs words in that <hi>Book,</hi> when I do not find any Expreſſions relating to any of theſe Particulars, that do either in words <hi>ſay</hi> ſo much, or will in the leaſt <hi>admit</hi> of any ſuch Inferences or Concluſions; (although as to this <hi>Third,</hi> if there were any word to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it might be defended.) For all the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> made uſe of by the <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> againſt the deſtroying of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> are either upon the account of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs, (which eſtabliſheth a Nation)</hi> or clearly in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Utility</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and not in the leaſt, upon any <hi>particular Affection</hi> to the <hi>People</hi> of that <hi>Country,</hi> as the <hi>Letter</hi> doth inſinuate the <hi>Pamphlet;</hi> being no otherwiſe concerned for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105626:3"/>them, than as it is, for preſerving the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> in oppoſition of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I find the <hi>Pamphlets</hi> commending the <hi>Dutch</hi> for their <hi>Morals,</hi> (compared with the <hi>French,</hi> &amp;c.) to be anſwered by objecting, that if the <hi>Author</hi> had lain but one night in any <hi>Inn</hi> of <hi>theirs,</hi> he would have been convinced of the contrary, which implieth, that he had never done it, or at leaſt never told the World he had, and yet the <hi>Book</hi> juſtifies his opinion of <hi>them</hi> in affirming his experience, from having travelled <hi>their Countries;</hi> (<hi>Intereſt of</hi> England, Page 30.) and truly by his general knowledge of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> he may well be ſuppoſed to have throughly done it; and granting ſo much, it conſequently follows, that he muſt then have experienced their <hi>Inns;</hi> but if from <hi>Couſening</hi> and <hi>Cheating</hi> in <hi>Inns, Ale-houſes</hi> and <hi>Taverns,</hi> the meaſures of a <hi>Peoples Morals</hi> muſt be Calculated; I fear ſome other <hi>Countries,</hi> by high <hi>Reckonings,</hi> falſe <hi>Meaſures,</hi> in <hi>Bottles, Pots</hi> and <hi>Cans,</hi> exceeding them, and tacitly allowed of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will be found as faulty as they, and to lye (at leaſt) equally with them, under the burden of that uncharitable <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> of blaming the whole for a part; for I can my ſelf by experience, ſo far joyn with the <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> in juſtifying of it, as to aver, That I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver travelled in all my Life, in any <hi>Country</hi> ſo cheap as in <hi>theirs,</hi> and that no private Perſon doth otherwiſe, but either <hi>voluntarily,</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profuſe, or <hi>careleſly</hi> in ſpending more than he needeth, in not keeping to his Ordinaries, but living at large; for their <hi>Rates</hi> by <hi>Land</hi> or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105626:4"/>
                     <hi>Water,</hi> are ſo certain, that none can pay one more than another, and the like is in <hi>their Inns,</hi> for <hi>Ordinaries</hi> and <hi>Lodgings;</hi> inſomuch that I have often wondred their great <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſneſs</hi> (which in all other places makes things dear) conſidered, I found living there ſo cheap as I did. But as no Number or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men, can be ſaid to be <hi>perfectly good,</hi> or <hi>altogether evil;</hi> ſo the moſt juſt and certain Rule for applauding or condemning any <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> is not from <hi>a few Inſtances</hi> of a ſmall part of it, but by way of <hi>Compariſon</hi> with other <hi>Countries;</hi> and by that <hi>Standard, Holland</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found by much ſo bad as <hi>Popiſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> where the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (which hath more or leſs an influence upon moſt of their <hi>Religion</hi>) of <hi>good Intentions, Probability</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> &amp;c. and of their whole Church, of <hi>keeping no Faith with Hereticks,</hi> &amp;c. is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with honeſt Converſation, rendring them unfit even for one anothers Society, there being no Fence againſt ſuch Principles.</p>
                  <p>The Cruelty at <hi>Amboina,</hi> is (I confeſs) to be had by all in Abhorrence; but ſince it was <hi>before</hi> we were born, that it was acted but by <hi>a few,</hi> and diſowned, and not juſtified <hi>at home:</hi> That King <hi>James</hi> of Happy Memory, and his wiſe and excellent Council and Favourites, thought therefore not fit to <hi>revenge</hi> it; and that it hath ſince, by ſeveral Treaties, been buried and put in Oblivion; I queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ought ſtill to <hi>remember</hi> it; but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that the conſtant Trade that the <hi>Popiſh Nations</hi> have (in all Ages down to our times) driven in <hi>Maſſacres</hi> and <hi>Cruel Torterings,</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105626:4"/>that with the applauſe and approbation of their chief <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Italy, Savoy, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> do witneſs, may be remembred, I can be well pleaſed, that that ſingle Act at <hi>Amboina,</hi> committed by a <hi>few Proteſtants</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the reſt, and which is abhorred by the <hi>Principles of their Religion,</hi> may not be forgotten; and thereupon the whole deſigns of the <hi>Pamphlet</hi> and <hi>Letter,</hi> each ſeverally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, I cannot obſerve, that they differ in any <hi>Material</hi> Circumſtance; but that both aim at the ſame end, the <hi>Honour, Greatneſs, Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> unleſs the <hi>firſt</hi> is too ſtraight laced in the Rules of Honeſty and Juſtice; believing (that though Intereſt rightly underſtood or miſtaken, governs all the World yet) that that Precept of <hi>doing to others as we would have them to do to us,</hi> gives no lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to any <hi>Country</hi> to deſtroy <hi>another,</hi> to the end to increaſe their own <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Greatneſs;</hi> for were it otherwiſe, nothing could be more for our Security againſt <hi>Invaſions</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of <hi>England,</hi> than to deſtroy in time the <hi>French</hi> in their Shipping, and thereby in their <hi>Maritime Commerce,</hi> before they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown in <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> in both, which from young <hi>Interlopers,</hi> they are in a ſhort time too much increaſed, eſpecially in our <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundland Fiſhery,</hi> where they have almoſt eaten us out, to the unſpeakable prejudice of the <hi>Weſtern Parts!</hi> though that <hi>Trade</hi> was once our <hi>greateſt Nurſery</hi> for <hi>Seamen,</hi> and might have been much more <hi>improved,</hi> and is of ſuch a <hi>Nature,</hi> as the <hi>Dutch</hi> were not capable of doing us much prejudice in,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105626:5"/>or at leaſt as they never <hi>attempted</hi> to do us any.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Letter</hi> reproves the <hi>Pamphlets inviting all Princes into the Triple League,</hi> ſcoffing at it as abſurd; <hi>the League being now determined,</hi> and to evince the Error, gives this account of the League: <hi>That the</hi> French King <hi>being entred</hi> Flanders, <hi>with a very powerful Army, the</hi> Kings <hi>of</hi> England, Sweden, <hi>and the</hi> States of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>entred into a Confederacy, with deſign to force the</hi> French <hi>to make Peace upon ſuch Terms as ſhould be propoſed by them,</hi> (and therein wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prevent the growing Greatneſs of <hi>France</hi>) <hi>and at the ſame time the</hi> Confederates <hi>made</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles <hi>amongſt themſelves, to help one another, in caſe any of them ſhould be invaded for having made this League, either by the</hi> French King, <hi>the</hi> King of Spain, <hi>or any of their Allies, and upon the acceptance of the Articles propoſed, the</hi> Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates <hi>became their</hi> Guarranty <hi>or</hi> Sureties, <hi>for performance of them on both ſides.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now, this being the State of the Caſe, where the Abſurdity or Bull lies, in making no diſtinction between the <hi>Triple League,</hi> and the <hi>Guarranty</hi> of the Peace, is beyond my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; for the <hi>League,</hi> as is confeſſed, being made to induce (that is to force) the <hi>French King</hi> to a Peace, (the <hi>King of Spain</hi>) who was Invaded, ſtanding in no need of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion) and the Confederacy continuing for warranting of the ſaid Agreement (which in effect is no leſs than an honeſt and prudent <hi>League,</hi> for keeping the <hi>French</hi> within toler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bounds and Limits) and for the aſſiſtance of each other againſt any that ſhould endeavour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105626:5"/>to revenge this Confederacy; the <hi>Triple League</hi> ſeems to me (as it is confeſſed by the <hi>Letter</hi> it ſelf, at the lower end of <hi>Page</hi> 15.) to be ſtill in being, and the Expreſſion to be as properly uſed as that of <hi>Guarranty,</hi> as being one and the ſame thing; for the <hi>Guarranty</hi> aiming at the ſame end the <hi>League</hi> doth, and being one Article of the Confederacy, the <hi>Triple League</hi> muſt be ſtill in being, as well as the <hi>Guarranty:</hi> And ſurely, it was the laſt <hi>Seſſion of Parliament</hi> thought ſo to be, when Money was deſired for maintaining of it. But this, <hi>Sir,</hi> is not worth contending about, for the matter being clearly laid down by the <hi>Letter,</hi> the judgment of it is left to your ſelf.</p>
                  <p>As I am no <hi>Statiſt,</hi> nor pretender to it, ſo it concerns not me to enquire further into the Articles agreed on by his Majeſty with the <hi>Swede</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> than is made publick, nor in the leaſt to attempt the Cenſuring any Action of <hi>State;</hi> (for that ſhall always be Foreign to me) but yet I preſume I may without offence ſay, it doth not appear to me, as it doth to the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Letter,</hi> that the <hi>Emperor</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> could not have been taken into the <hi>Triple League</hi> by the <hi>Confederates,</hi> without engaging to aſſiſt them upon occaſion againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> for as we find that it hath been ordinary for <hi>Princes</hi> to limit and proportion their <hi>Leagues,</hi> according to their <hi>Intereſts,</hi> ſo it is irrational to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. And it doth not follow, that becauſe it is the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Emperor</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> to enter into a <hi>League</hi> with other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105626:6"/>
                     <hi>Princes,</hi> for keeping the <hi>French King</hi> from unjuſtly incroaching upon his <hi>Neighbours,</hi> that therefore thoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> contrary to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Intereſt,</hi> ſhould enter into a <hi>League</hi> with them againſt the <hi>Turk:</hi> But I Honour the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of the <hi>Letter,</hi> for the care he expreſſeth to have for the prevention of <hi>War</hi> to this <hi>Nation,</hi> and for the reſt and quiet of the poor People of <hi>England,</hi> (Page 9.)</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Pamphlet</hi> not being concerned in the complaint againſt thoſe that blame the breach with <hi>Holland,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Tripple League,</hi> I ſhall paſs that over, agreeing fully with the <hi>Author,</hi> that Self-preſervation is chiefly to be preferred, <hi>Salus Populi ſuprema Lex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Letter,</hi> in his treating of the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> hath ſeveral <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations</hi> and <hi>Notions</hi> deſerving conſideration, which I ſhall reduce to theſe ſix Heads follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>That our Increaſe in Power, ſince the time of Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>(of famous Memory) is not proportionable to the increaſe of the</hi> Dutch, (Page 12.)</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>That the</hi> Dutch, <hi>being ſo powerful at Sea as they now are, may, by joyning with the</hi> French, <hi>(whenever they will agree upon it) endanger the Conqueſt of</hi> England; <hi>and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themſelves the moſt conſiderable parts in it for Trade, being Maſters at Sea, provide for their own Security againſt the greatneſs of</hi> France, (Page 12.)</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>That it is not Wiſdom for any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to have its Safety depend upon the Prudence of another, as in relying upon its being againſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105626:6"/>the</hi> Intereſt of Holland <hi>to Invade</hi> England, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may miſtake their Intereſt,</hi> (Page 12.)</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>That a Conqueſt of</hi> England <hi>being made, the</hi> Dutch <hi>Government being more eaſie and indulging Trade, than the Arbitrary and Severe Regiment of</hi> France, <hi>as alſo their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion concurring more with ours than that of</hi> France, <hi>the Trading Party of</hi> England <hi>would be likelier to cloſe with the firſt than the latter; and for the like Reaſon ſhould</hi> Holland <hi>be ever in danger of a Conqueſt by the Conjunction of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>with</hi> France, <hi>they would rather chooſe to become part of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government, than ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Power of</hi> France: <hi>For that their joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us, and therein making it as much our Intereſt to promote their Trade, as the Trade of any other Nation, may anſwer that Objection,</hi> That their fear of our obſtructing their Trade, will make them averſe to us, (<hi>Page</hi> 13.)</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <hi>That it is not probable, that the</hi> Dutch <hi>will ever agree to put themſelves under the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the</hi> French, <hi>who will not truſt them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Advantages as may compel them to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Promiſes, as the other will never give them ſuch a Power, leſt they ſhould make a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt uſe of it,</hi> (Page 14.)</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, <hi>That conſidering the Situation and Conſtitutions of</hi> England, <hi>a Coalition with us would prove more acceptable and advantageous to them, than any Terms they can expect from the</hi> French; <hi>and that ſhould we get no more than the</hi> Maritime Towns, <hi>and the</hi> French <hi>all the reſt of the</hi> States Dominions, <hi>we ſhould have no cauſe to repent our Bargain,</hi> (Page 14.)</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105626:7"/>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Notions</hi> contain the ſubſtance of that part of the <hi>Letter</hi> which treats of the <hi>Intereſt of England;</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> of which I muſt not at preſent deny, becauſe the <hi>Auxiliary</hi> aſſiſtance which we have received from <hi>France,</hi> ſeems to make it good; yet the <hi>Story</hi> of 88. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us, that the <hi>States</hi> in thoſe times, with 35 <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> Blocked up <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi>'s <hi>Navy</hi> in it, to the great Service of <hi>England;</hi> but it is certain, that all <hi>Nations</hi> will increaſe, or decline more or leſs, according as their <hi>Intereſt</hi> is purſued, and their Government ſuited to it, which happily is the Cauſe, why none can be ſaid to have out-done the States of <hi>Holland</hi> (their low beginnings conſidered) in increaſe in <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Riches;</hi> but if Augmentation in Territories, and Power be a Crime, it is one that <hi>France</hi> is more guilty of than the <hi>United Netherlands,</hi> and ought therefore to be looked upon with a more jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Eye; for the natural advantages that we have of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the Situation of our <hi>Country,</hi> and the greatneſs of it; in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and number of our <hi>Havens</hi> and <hi>Ports,</hi> to breed <hi>Seamen,</hi> and harbour <hi>Ships,</hi> are ſuch, as appears to me to render it impoſſible for them, ever to become our Superiors at Sea (<hi>as is ſuggeſted by the Letter,</hi> Page 11.)</p>
                  <p>As to the <hi>ſecond</hi> Aſſertion, or Head, I muſt in that crave leave to diſſent, without grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the queſtion (which is begged) that <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whilſt in Liberty, might be under a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of agreeing with <hi>France</hi> for the Conqueſt of <hi>England,</hi> the thing ſeeming to me to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105626:7"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> From their want of <hi>People,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fit for <hi>War,</hi> their <hi>Dominions</hi> being ſmall, and furniſhed much with <hi>Strangers,</hi> and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with <hi>Traders,</hi> Circumſtances which no <hi>Country</hi> muſt be under, that deſigns Foreign Conqueſts or Invaſions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Nature of their <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in its being no more than an <hi>Union</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Abſolute Sovereignties,</hi> for common De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Preſervation, which is a Quality not fit for Acquiſitions, in that the Difficulty in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying every concern upon the good Succeſs of their Arms, and the many occaſions that would ariſe from thence of Differences amongſt them, renders it impracticable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the Impoſſibility of the <hi>French,</hi> and their <hi>Agreement upon the Diviſion of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland; for that it is not to be imagined, but each of them would be jealous of the others <hi>Increaſe in Territories and Power,</hi> and that the <hi>States</hi> would have no more cauſe to preſume upon their over-witting the <hi>French,</hi> in getting to themſelves the moſt conſiderable places in it for <hi>Trade,</hi> (as is ſuppoſed by the <hi>Letter</hi> Page 12.) than the <hi>French</hi> in over-reaching <hi>them,</hi> who have always been wiſe enough in <hi>Treaties:</hi> For that an increaſe in the <hi>French Monarchy</hi> would be more dangerous to the <hi>States,</hi> than the like in the <hi>States</hi> would be to <hi>them,</hi> who are already the others overmatch; and it cannot with reaſon but be ſuppoſed, that in the <hi>Diviſion of England,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> would on the one hand have an Eye at ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves with that they only want, for making them uncontrolable in the World,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105626:8"/>
                     <hi>good Havens</hi> and <hi>Ports,</hi> and alſo on the other hand, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> would never yield unto that that would <hi>deſtroy them.</hi> But if <hi>England</hi> had reaſon to be jealous of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Hollands</hi> Conjunction, in order to the Conqueſt of it, (as the Letter ſuggeſts:) I fear with the ſame reaſon <hi>France</hi> will be jealous of <hi>England</hi>'s im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patronizing <hi>Holland,</hi> as being as well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to have the <hi>Dominion of the Seas</hi> ſo much <hi>undivided</hi> in the hands of any <hi>one</hi> Lord, as all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> cannot check it, as <hi>we</hi> are to have the <hi>Dominion</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> in the like kind under any other Lord or Prince.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>Third</hi> Aſſertion, I have not any thing to object in oppoſition, nothing being more ordinary in the World, than <hi>groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes</hi> in the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of Countries, proceeding often from <hi>Paſſion, Revenge,</hi> and <hi>diſordered Affections;</hi> yet this may be ſaid in the Caſe, that the <hi>States</hi> were ſuch great Maſters in the knowledge of their Civil Intereſts, that <hi>none</hi> might have been <hi>Safelier</hi> truſted upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than <hi>they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the <hi>Fourth Head</hi> or Aſſertion, I have only this to anſwer, That as it is natural for all Rational Creatures, of <hi>two Evils</hi> to chooſe the <hi>leaſt,</hi> ſo ſuppoſing that the <hi>States</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a neceſſity of parting with their own Government, <hi>will have the Election</hi> of their <hi>new</hi> Lords in their own <hi>Power;</hi> and taking it for granted, that they are Men of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> I do fully agree with the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Letter</hi> in his opinion, that they will in ſuch Caſe chooſe rather the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> than the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105626:8"/>Severe Government of the <hi>French,</hi> unleſs the conſideration (in their partial opinion) of who is beſt able to protect their Country, do not prevail with them, to <hi>truſt</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King in point of <hi>Religion;</hi> but I very much queſtion, whether it is not groundleſs to ſuppoſe, that any Nation being attacked by <hi>two</hi> great <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, will have</hi> the <hi>choice</hi> of their own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters left to themſelves, by a <hi>mutual Agreement</hi> betwixt thoſe Monarchs, without which it cannot be. But I highly eſteem the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Letter,</hi> for the true Senſe he expreſſeth to have of the <hi>French</hi> Government, from which the <hi>Lord in Mercy deliver all other Countries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> Aſſertion, is a Suppoſition that the <hi>Dutch</hi> will have it in their <hi>choice,</hi> to truſt the <hi>French</hi> or not, and in <hi>ſuch</hi> Caſe I am of opinion with the <hi>Letter,</hi> that they will never do it, <hi>Spain, Lorrain,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> being a ſufficient <hi>warning</hi> to them; but as Affairs now ſtand, I very much fear they will not have the <hi>Election</hi> of it in their own hands.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sixth</hi> Aſſertion, though as moſt <hi>weighty,</hi> deſerveth moſt <hi>Conſideration;</hi> yet for the <hi>firſt</hi> part of it, Whether <hi>England</hi> admitting the <hi>Dutch</hi> to a <hi>Coalition,</hi> would be of more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to them, than any Terms they can expect from the <hi>French.</hi> I will not diſpute, but am much of belief, that the <hi>French</hi> Councils, conſidering that they want nothing to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their <hi>univerſal</hi> deſign more than an Intereſt in the <hi>Northern</hi> Seas, where they might Harbour and Form a <hi>Navy,</hi> nouriſh and breed <hi>Seamen;</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105626:9"/>and likewiſe conſidering, that the Maritime Towns of <hi>Holland, Zealand</hi> and <hi>Friezland,</hi> would ſignifie nothing without <hi>Trade,</hi> but in danger of being ſwallowed up by the <hi>Sea,</hi> for want of Ability to maintain the <hi>Banks</hi> againſt it, nor <hi>Trade</hi> ſignifie any thing without Liberty; they would ſoon find it neceſſary as to their Intereſt, to wave the <hi>French</hi> Principles for <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government, and to leave the <hi>Dutch</hi> in a great meaſure of <hi>Freedom,</hi> relying only upon <hi>Citadels,</hi> for keeping them dependent upon them, and forcing them upon occaſion to be uſeful to them, as judging <hi>that</hi> the beſt way to ſerve themſelves of them, leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by <hi>Severity,</hi> they ſhould provoke the <hi>diſperſing</hi> the Inhabitants to <hi>Emden, Bremen, Hambourg, Lubeck</hi> and <hi>Dantzick,</hi> &amp;c. the four firſt being <hi>Imperial Free</hi> Cities, and the latter the <hi>ſame</hi> under <hi>Poland;</hi> for <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government, (that muſt be maintained by the Sword) and the idle Callings and rude man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Souldiers,</hi> which are altogether incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with, and <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce,</hi> will always cauſe <hi>Traders</hi> to change <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> for <hi>Liberty,</hi> or at leaſt in hopes of better Entertainment, one <hi>Country</hi> for another, as did the Subverſion of the <hi>Florentine</hi> Government in <hi>that</hi> Country; and as they were preparing to do the like in <hi>Holland,</hi> when they feared the late <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi>'s overturning <hi>that</hi> State; for the <hi>Antipathy</hi> betwixt <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> is ſuch, that all Monarchs of <hi>Trading</hi> Countries have ever held it their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to keep their great <hi>Trading Towns</hi> free from a <hi>Mercenary Militia,</hi> and it is exceeding
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105626:9"/>difficult, if not Morally impoſſible for a Prince to advance <hi>Trade</hi> to any great <hi>height,</hi> where the People are under the awe of a ſtanding <hi>Military Power;</hi> and the <hi>French King</hi> ſeems to own the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> in that finding the benefit of Commerce, he is even in <hi>France</hi> content that his <hi>Trading Cities</hi> ſhould be freed from <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and more gently uſed than the reſt of his Country; for ſo far as the Nature of his <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government will permit, he ſtudieth all manner of ways to advance <hi>Trade.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As <hi>Firſt,</hi> By totally prohibiting ſuch <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Commodities</hi> and <hi>Manufactures,</hi> as his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are capable of making, ſufficient to ſerve his Country, as <hi>Train-Oyl,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> By burthening <hi>others</hi> with high <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> to the end to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage his <hi>own</hi> Artiſans and Seamen, thereby making the Trade of <hi>England</hi> thither very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to us, our <hi>Tranſportations</hi> hence being inconſiderable to our <hi>Importations</hi> thence; and as they <hi>improve</hi> in any Faculty, ſo they either <hi>Prohibit</hi> or <hi>Increaſe</hi> their Impoſitions, upon the Importation of the Foreign-made Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that Faculty.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As an Incouragement to Trade, the <hi>French</hi> King hath lately declared the Exerciſe of Commerce in a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> to be no prejudice to his <hi>Quality,</hi> having alſo erected an <hi>Academy</hi> for breeding his <hi>Nobility</hi> to Sea Affairs, and teaching them the Art of <hi>Navigation,</hi> &amp;c. All which may well Alarm <hi>England</hi> to a <hi>Jealouſie</hi> of their Deſigns, as moſt dangerous to it, and to look upon the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105626:10"/>
                     <hi>French,</hi> as thoſe Rivals, whom (if hatred be <hi>lawful,</hi> as the <hi>Letter</hi> in this Caſe ſeems to make it) we ought moſt to hate; for ſhould they once come to <hi>Vie</hi> with us in <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Naval</hi> ſtrength, we ſhould find them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all that ever went before them, in <hi>Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Selfiſhneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whether the ſecond part of this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath a good <hi>Foundation,</hi> which aſſerts, <hi>That ſhould</hi> England <hi>get but the</hi> Sea Towns <hi>alone, leaving the reſt of the</hi> States Dominions <hi>to the</hi> French, <hi>we ſhould have no cauſe to repent our Bargain.</hi> I will not preſume to <hi>judge,</hi> yet <hi>this</hi> I think <hi>conſiderable</hi> in the Caſe, that ſhould the <hi>Inlands</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and with them all the <hi>Conquered places</hi> fall to the ſhare of the <hi>French,</hi> as by the late pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Propoſals</hi> in <hi>Dutch</hi> (if true) they ſeem to pretend unto the <hi>Letter;</hi> then having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the command of the Rivers of <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Maſe,</hi> &amp;c. together with <hi>Sluce,</hi> and the other Garriſons which ſhut up the Trade of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> they will have it in their Power to render all the parts of the Seventeen Provinces, which will remain to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> of no more uſe to them, than they pleaſe to allow of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Sea-Towns</hi> of the <hi>United Netherlands</hi> cannot be divided from the <hi>Inlands,</hi> from which they receive their <hi>nouriſhment,</hi> nor deprived of the uſe of their <hi>Rivers,</hi> by which they drive their <hi>Trades,</hi> without utter <hi>ruine</hi> to them, and making them thereby an intolerable <hi>Burthen</hi> to their <hi>Maſters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105626:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> will thereby be ſo invironed, or rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguered by the <hi>French</hi> Garriſons and Forces on all ſides, as well towards <hi>Germany, Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp;c. as towards <hi>France;</hi> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no means left them, for forming or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Army, (as any that know thoſe Countries muſt confeſs) they will always be at the <hi>French King's</hi> Devotion, and when aſſaulted by him, without poſſibility of contributing any conſiderable aſſiſtance to their own <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> or to make the <hi>Triple League</hi> of any uſe to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe ſuch will be the enervated condition of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> will be neceſſitated, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to <hi>maintain</hi> them longer than the <hi>French</hi> will <hi>permit</hi> him, either to quit them voluntarily, or (if he can obtain ſo much <hi>Favour</hi>) to make an exchange or Sale of them to the <hi>French</hi> King, who then having <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> (which he hath ſo long thirſted after) and all the <hi>Rivers</hi> belonging to them in his own hands, will aſſuredly, for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>own Countries,</hi> even in times of <hi>Peace,</hi> ſo <hi>obſtruct</hi> and <hi>hinder</hi> the Trade of the Maritime Towns of <hi>Holland, Zealand</hi> and <hi>Friezland,</hi> (if in the poſſeſſion of any but himſelf) and in times of <hi>War</hi> totally ſhut them up by Land) as will reſtore <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> to their ancient Trade, and make a new <hi>Holland</hi> of them; which being in the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> will probably prove abundantly worſe to <hi>England</hi> than the old, if large <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> of Injuries and Injuſtices, committed in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105626:11"/>Trade by them againſt this Nation, may war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant a Concluſion; as by the Certificate under the Lord Ambaſſador <hi>Hollis</hi> his hand, (which I ſend you here incloſed) given upon an order of his Majeſties Privy-Council, Dated the 17th of <hi>April</hi> 1667. in the Caſe of Sir <hi>Francis Toppe</hi> and Company, doth for one inſtance ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appear.</p>
                  <p>Nay, ſuch is the <hi>envious</hi> care of the <hi>French,</hi> that no Nation ſhould <hi>Get</hi> or <hi>Thrive</hi> by <hi>them,</hi> that (as Mr. <hi>Samuel Fortrey,</hi> one of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of his Majeſties Privy-Chamber, reporteth in his Book Printed 1663. and Dedicated to <hi>King Charles the Second</hi>) not many years ago, they ſuſpecting (through miſtakes) that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> had an advantage of them in their Trade for <hi>France,</hi> they were upon Counſels for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting</hi> all Trade with <hi>England,</hi> until upon a ſtrict examination, they found, that whereas <hi>England</hi> vented of their Commodities into <hi>France,</hi> not to above the value of <hi>Ten hundred thouſand pounds per Annum; France</hi> vented of theirs to the <hi>Engliſh Six and twenty hundred thouſand Pounds;</hi> and then finding that they had <hi>Sixteen hundred thouſand Pounds</hi> advantage in the Ballance, they ſoon let fall their deſign, though yet not without <hi>burthening Engliſh</hi> Manufactures with <hi>New Impoſitions,</hi> in ſuch manner, as might much hinder the vent of them in their Country. Mr. <hi>Fortrey</hi> in the aforementioned <hi>Book,</hi> doth not only recite the very <hi>Ballance</hi> of <hi>Trade</hi> it ſelf, which he affirms was preſented to the <hi>French</hi> King, to ſhew the advantage they have in their Trade with <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> but alſo adds further, that hereby it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105626:11"/>may appear, how inſenſibly our <hi>Treaſure</hi> will be <hi>Exhauſted,</hi> and the Nation <hi>Beggered,</hi> whilſt we careleſly neglect our own Intereſt, and <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers abroad</hi> are diligent to make their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by us.</p>
                  <p>And it is of no little conſideration, that the French ſhould ſo far <hi>Overvalue</hi> themſelves, as to increaſe their Impoſitions upon Dutch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, to a degree of Prohibiting them, and deny to the Dutch the like Power by theirs, as if they had a right to deal as they pleaſe towards other Nations, and yet none to do towards them (by way of Retaliation) any more than they ſhall think fit to give them <hi>leave</hi> to do; an overweening opinion of their own Greatneſs, which all Princes and States ought to be Jealous of, as not knowing where their Ambition will end.</p>
                  <p>And beſides theſe things thus inſtanced in, we have great cauſe to take notice, that as the effect of the implacable Hatred of the French to our Nation, they cannot forbear in their Writings, to expreſs their Inveterate Malice againſt us, as that Book called, <hi>Le Politique de France,</hi> writ in the year 1669. and Dedicated to the French King, is a pregnant Teſtimony, where no better <hi>Epithets</hi> are allowed us, than being <hi>without Friends, without Faith, without Religion, without Honeſty, without any Juſtice,</hi> of <hi>defying</hi> or <hi>provoking Natures, light</hi> or <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant to the higheſt degree, Cruel, Impatient, Gluttons, Proud, Audacious and Covetous, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for ready Execution and Aſſaults; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of managing a War with judgment.</hi> With other ſuch-like opprobrious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105626:12"/>Expreſſions, beſides a Method pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to be obſerved in order to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>England,</hi> Page 158, 159, 160, 161. enough to raiſe a lawful Indignation in all true Engliſh-men, againſt ſuch Inſolent Slanderers, who by their Impudence, endeavour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their own Characters upon us, contrary to the known experience of the reſt of the World.</p>
                  <p>And now, Sir, I have no more to add, than (all Circumſtances conſidered) my Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Pamphlet in this Principle, that while <hi>France</hi> is ſo Great as at preſent, it can in no kind be for the Safety of <hi>England</hi> to ſubvert <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> &amp;c. which are properly called their Out-guards or Works againſt all Invaſions, and cannot be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, or in the hands of the French, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out laying <hi>England</hi> Naked, or at leaſt the more open to that Nation, and that nothing is more demonſtrable, than that ſince the United Provinces cannot ſignifie much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Freedom, they will under their own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be of moſt uſe to all Chriſtendom, (ſave <hi>France,</hi> who only wants them as a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification for threatning, inſtead of courting their Neighbours) in maintaining the general Ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> even as it was great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the long Parliament (for <hi>the wickedeſt of men may have Worldly Prudence</hi>) to joyn with <hi>Holland</hi> in the preſerving of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as neceſſary for the Ballancing of <hi>Sweden,</hi> when <hi>Cromwel</hi> (in his time) in revenge of manifeſt Affronts and hatred, had deſigned the ruine of the <hi>Dane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105626:12"/>
                  <p>And thus, Sir, having in Obedience to your Commands, given you freely my ſenſe of the Pamphlet and Letter, without varying from the matter in either; as it is in them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively ſtated, I hope you will pardon any thing wherein I may differ with you in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Opinion; for I have this for my Buckler, that what I have writ is Truth, and that I aim at nothing in it, but the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the King and Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and Proteſtant Religion, denying that any can have more Cordial Affection for them, than my ſelf, who am <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="certificate">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105626:13"/>
                  <head>April <hi>17.</hi> Anno <hi>1669. According to the Printed Copy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN Obedience to an Order of Council of the 16th. preſent, requiring my opinion, what is fit to be done for relief of Sir <hi>Francis Toppe</hi> and Company: I do humbly certifie, that I have peruſed their Caſe, and find that they complain of great Loſſes and Damages ſuſtained in the Year <hi>1644.</hi> whilſt they lived in St. <hi>Malo,</hi> from the <hi>French,</hi> by ſeizing their Goods in a time of Peace, in the very Harbours of <hi>France,</hi> whither they had brought thoſe Goods in a way of Trading, and where by ſeveral Treaties then in force, and by the very Law of Nations, (which gives a Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Perſons and Eſtates of all who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Peaceably within the Dominions of any Prince or State) they ought to have been Safe and Free from all Arreſts, the Owners not having done any thing whereby to Forfeit their Intereſt in them; which Courſe, if ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, muſt needs be the Deſtruction of all Trade and Commerce between the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, as it is alſo very Diſhonourable and Injurious to his Majeſty, that the Publick
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105626:13"/>Faith ſhould be broken to his Subjects, who Trade under his Protection, by vertue of the Treaties made between the two Crowns; and it is much to be feared, that the Proceedings in <hi>France</hi> may become very prejudicial in this kind, to the whole Trading of the Engliſh Nation in that Kingdom, if nothing be done to ſtop this growing miſchief: In regard this is not the ſingle Caſe, where this courſe hath been put in practice, the like having been done ſeveral times to Engliſh Merchants at <hi>Rouen,</hi> who are not yet free of the trouble; for a Capture at Sea, whether real, or pretended to have been made in <hi>1616.</hi> by an Engliſh Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateer of a French Ship, belonging to one <hi>Delauziay,</hi> valued but at ſix thouſand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. And whilſt I had the Honour to ſerve his Majeſty, as his Ambaſſador in <hi>France,</hi> two Engliſh Ships coming into Harbour at <hi>Marſeille,</hi> when they had Landed their Goods, and paid all Duties, were ſeized upon, Ships and Goods, and notwithſtanding all my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations, would not be diſcharged: But ſome Months after, the War breaking out, were given to the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company there, they pretending ſome Ships of theirs to have been formerly taken by the Engliſh. And now, as I hear at St. <hi>John de Liez,</hi> the ſame <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage is threatned, if not already begun, to our Merchants there, for the Reparation of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105626:14"/>the Widow <hi>de Lazin,</hi> for ſome Goods of her late Husbands, taken from her by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>1643.</hi> So as all this makes me fearful it may come to be a conſtant Cuſtom, if not prevented. I do therefore offer it as my humble Opinion, that all care ſhould be taken for the prevention of it. And for this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſe of Sir <hi>Francis Toppe</hi>'s and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that in the firſt place a fair Application may be made to the French King, as well by his Ambaſſador here, as by his Majeſties Ambaſſador at <hi>Paris,</hi> for the juſt Satisfaction of the Petitioners, which may be hoped will prove effectual, and ſhould it not, it will then be time for his Majeſty to conſider, what is further to be done for the Vindication of his own Honour, and the Protection of his Subjects.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HOLLIS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105626:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE WORLDS MISTAKE IN <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> OR, A Short Political Diſcourſe, SHEWING, That CROMWELL's Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtration, (during his Four Years and Nine Months pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Protectorſhip) laid the Foundation of our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, in the Decay of TRADE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:105626:15"/>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105626:15"/>
                  <head>THE WORLDS MISTAKE IN <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>OF all the Sins that the Children of Men are guilty of, there is none that our corrupt Natures are more inclinable unto, than that of Idolatry, a Sin that may be towards Men ſo well as other Creatures and things: For as that which a Man unmeaſurably relies, and ſets his Heart upon, is called his God, even as that which he falls down before and worſhippeth: So when one hath the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of another in an exceſs of admiration, whether for Greatneſs or Richneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we are ſubject to adore, we are ſaid to Idolize him; and therefore the wiſe <hi>Venetians,</hi> who, of all Men, are moſt Jealous of their Liberty, conſidering, that as the Nature of Man is not prone to any thing more than the Adoration of Men, ſo nothing is more Deſtructive to Freedom, have, for preventing the Miſchiefs of it, made it Unlawful, even ſo much as to Mourn for their Duke at his Death: Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating thereby, that their Felicity and Safety
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105626:16"/>depends not upon the uncertain Thred of any one Man's Life, but upon the Vertue of their good Laws and Orders well executed, and that they can never want vertuous Perſons to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: And how do ſuch Principles in Men, led by little more than Morality, reprove thoſe who have a great meaſure of Goſpel-light, for their ſenſleſs Exceſs, in their adoring the remembrance of <hi>Cromwell?</hi> For as the Objects of Idolatry are Miſtaken Creatures, or things proceeding ſometimes from Self-love, ſo well as other Cauſes; So the undeſerved Approbation and Applauſe, that <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Memory ſeems to have with his Adherents, amounting to little leſs than the Idolizing of him, appears to me, to be the product of an exceſſive Veneration of Greatneſs, and a Selfiſh Partiality towards him; for that the more Honour is given to him, the more Praiſe they think will conſequently redound to them who were his Favourites; and they fortifie themſelves herein, with the Credit they ſay he hath abroad, though there is little in that, becauſe the opinion that Strangers have of him, may well be put upon the accompt of their Ignorance in the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> which Travellers do find to be ſo great, even amongſt Miniſters of State, as is to be admired. And now as this Error in Idolizing <hi>Oliver</hi> hath two Moral Evils in it, (beſides the ſin in it ſelf:) The one a Reflection upon the preſent Times, as if the former were better than theſe. And the other the unjuſt Defrauding the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> of that which is due to them, to give it Idolatrouſly to him to whom it doth not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105626:16"/>belong; I eſteem it a Duty incumbent upon me, to diſcover the Miſtake. I am not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, that I ſhall by this, drawn the Envy of thoſe upon me, who being Jealous of their Honour, will be angry for touching them in their <hi>Diana;</hi> but knowing my ſelf clear from the Vices of Envying Vertue in any, how contrary ſoever he may be to me in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo well as from being unwilling to allow every one their due Commendations, I will caſt my ſelf upon Providence for the Succeſs of this Paper; and in reference to <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Government, and the preſent times, make ſome Obſervations relating to both; and, in order thereunto, ſhew,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That the Original Cauſe of the low Condition that we are now (in relation to Trade) reduced unto, had its beginning in <hi>Oliver</hi>'s time, and the Foundations of it laid, either by his ignorant miſtaking the Intereſt of this Kingdom, or willfully doing it, for the Advancement of his own particular Intereſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That his time, for the ſhort conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, had as much of Oppreſſion and Injuſtice, as any former times.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly and laſtly, That he never in his later days, valued either Honour or Honeſty, when they ſtood in the way of his Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that there is nothing to be admired in him (though ſo much Idolized) but that the Partiality of the World ſhould make him ſo great a Favourite of Ignorance and Forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as he ſeems to be.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105626:17"/>
                  <p>When this late Tyrant, or Protector, (as ſome call him) turned out the <hi>Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the Kingdom was arrived at the higheſt pitch of Trade, Wealth and Honour, that it, in any Age, ever yet knew. The Trade appeared, by the great Sums offered then for the Cuſtoms and Exciſe, Nine hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds a year being refuſed. The Riches of the Nation ſhewed it ſelf, in the high Value that Land and all our Native Commodities bore, which are the certain Marks of Opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. Our Honour was made known to all the World, by a Conquering Navy, which had brought the <hi>Hollanders</hi> upon their Knees, to beg Peace of us upon our own Conditions, keeping all other Nations in awe. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe Advantages, the Publick Stock was Five hundred thouſand Pounds in ready Money, the value of Seven hundred thouſand Pounds in Stores, and the whole Army in Advance, ſome Four, and none under Two Months; ſo that though there might be a Debt of near Five hundred thouſand Pounds upon the Kingdom, he met with above twice the value in lieu of it.</p>
                  <p>The Nation being in this flouriſhing and formidable Poſture, <hi>Cromwell</hi> began his Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, upon the greateſt Advantages ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, having it in his power to have made Peace and profitable Leagues, in what manner he had pleaſed, with all our Neighbours, every one courting us then, and being ambitious of the Friendſhip of <hi>England;</hi> but, as if the Lord had infatuated and deprived him of common Senſe and Reaſon, he neglected all our Golden
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105626:17"/>Opportunities, miſimproved the Victory God had given us over the <hi>United Natherlands,</hi> making Peace (without ever ſtriking ſtroak) ſo ſoon as ever things come into his hands, upon equal Terms with them. And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after, contrary to our Intereſt, made an unjuſt War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and an Impolitick League with <hi>France,</hi> bringing the firſt thereby under, and making the latter too great for Chriſtendom; and by that means, broke the Ballance betwixt the two Crowns of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> which his Predeceſſors, the Long Parliament, had always wiſely preſerved.</p>
                  <p>In this Diſhoneſt War with <hi>Spain,</hi> he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and endeavoured to impoſe a Belief upon the World, that he had nothing in his eye, but the Advancement of the Proteſtant Cauſe, and the Honour of this Nation; but his pretences were either fraudulent, or he was ignorant in Foreign Affairs (as I am apt to think, that he was not guilty of too much knowledge in them.) For he that had known any thing of the temper of the Popiſh Prelacy, and the French Court Policies, could not but ſee, that the way to increaſe or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Reformed Intereſt in <hi>France,</hi> was by rendring the Proteſtants of neceſſary uſe to their King; for that longer than they were ſo, they could not be free from Perſecution; and that the way to render them ſo, was by keeping the Ballance betwixt <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> even, as that which would conſequently make them uſeful to their King: But by overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ballance in his War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and joyning with <hi>France,</hi> he freed the French
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105626:18"/>King from his Fears of <hi>Spain,</hi> inabled him to ſubdue all Factions at home, and thereby to bring himſelf into a condition of not ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in need of any of them; and from thence hath proceeded the Perſecution that hath ſince been, and ſtill is, in that Nation, againſt the Reformed there; ſo that <hi>Oliver,</hi> inſtead of advancing the Reformed Intereſt, hath by an Error in his Politicks, been the Author of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying it.</p>
                  <p>The Honour and Advantage he propounded to this Nation, in his pulling down of <hi>Spain,</hi> had as ill a Foundation: For if true as was ſaid, that we were to have had <hi>Oſtend</hi> and <hi>Newport,</hi> ſo well as <hi>Dunkirk</hi> (when we could get them) they bore no proportion in any kind, to all the reſt of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s European Dominions, which muſt neceſſarily have fallen to the French King's ſhare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their joyning, and nearneſs to him, and remoteneſs from us; and the increaſing the Greatneſs of ſo near a Neighbour, muſt have increaſed our future Dangers. But this Man, who through Ignorance is ſo ſtrangely cried up in the World, was not guilty of this Error in State only, but committed as great a Soleciſm in his deſigning the Outing of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and ſetting up of the King of <hi>Sweden:</hi> For had the Sweeds but got <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> (as in all probability, had <hi>Oliver</hi> lived, they would have done) they had wanted nothing of Conſequence, but the Cities of <hi>Lubeck</hi> and <hi>Dantzick,</hi> (which by their then Potency they would eaſily have gained) of being Maſters of the whole <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105626:18"/>both ſides, from the Sound or Mouth, down to the bottom of it; by which, together with all <hi>Denmark, Norway,</hi> and the Danes part of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> which would conſequently have been theirs (they then having, as they ſtill have, the Land of <hi>Bremen</hi>) there would have been nothing, but the ſmall Counties of <hi>Oulden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-Friezland,</hi> (which would eaſily have fallen into their mouths) betwixt them and the <hi>United Netherlands,</hi> whereby <hi>Sweden</hi> would on the one ſide to the North and North-Eaſt, have been as great, as <hi>France</hi> on the other, to the South and South-Weſt; and they two able to have divided the Weſtern Empire betwixt them.</p>
                  <p>And whereas it had in all Ages been the Policies of the Northern States and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, to keep the Dominion of the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea divided amongſt ſeveral petty Princes and States, that no one might be ſole Maſter of it; becauſe otherwiſe moſt of the neceſſary Commodities for Shiping, coming from thence and <hi>Norway,</hi> any one Lord of the whole, might lay up the Shiping of <hi>Europe</hi> by the walls, in ſhutting only of his Ports, and denying the Commodities of his Country to other States. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> contrary to this wiſe Maxim, endeavoured to put the whole <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea into the Sweeds hands, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly had (though I ſuppoſe ignorantly) done it, if his death had not given them that ſucceeded him, the Long Parliament, an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of prudently preventing it: For if he had underſtood the Importance of the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea to this Nation, he could not have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105626:19"/>been ſo Impolitick, as to have projected ſo dangerous a deſign againſt his new <hi>Utopia,</hi> as giving the opening and ſhutting of it to any one Prince. I am not ignorant that this error is excuſed, by pretending that we were to have had <hi>Elſinore</hi> and <hi>Gronenburg</hi> Caſtle, (the firſt, the Town, upon the narrow entrance of the <hi>Baltick,</hi> called the Sound, where all Ships Ride, and pay T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l to the King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and the latter, the Fortreſs that defends both Town and Ships) by which we ſhould have been Maſters of the Sound, and conſequently of the <hi>Baltick;</hi> but they that know thoſe Countries, and how great a Prince the Sweed would have been, had he obtained all the reſt, beſides theſe two Bables, muſt confeſs, we ſhould have been at his Devotion, in our holding of any thing in his Countries: And further, if the dangerous conſequence of ſetting up ſo great a Prince, had not been in the caſe, it had been againſt the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> to have had an Obligation upon us to maintain places ſo remote, againſt the Enmity of many States and Princes; and that for theſe Reaſons:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the ordinary Tolls of the Sound would not have defrayed half the charge; and to have taken more than the ordinary Tolls, we could not have done, without draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a general Quarrel upon us, from moſt of the Princes and States of the Northern parts of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe the Experience of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times ſheweth us, that Foreign Acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions have ever been Chargeable and Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105626:19"/>to the People of <hi>England;</hi> as Sir <hi>Robert Cotton</hi> makes it clearly appear, That not only all thoſe Pieces of <hi>France,</hi> which belonged to us by rightful Succeſſion; but alſo thoſe we held by Conqueſt, were always great burthens to our Nation, and cauſe of much Poverty and Miſery to the People. And it is not our Caſe alone, to be the worſe for Conqueſts, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though more ours than other Countries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Charge and uncertainty of the Winds and Weather in the Tranſportation of Succors and Relief by Sea, which contiguous Territories, which are upon the Main, are not ſubject to,) but the Caſe alſo of (I think I may ſay) all other Kingdoms. In <hi>France</hi> their Burthens and Oppreſſions have grown in all Ages, with the greatneſs of their Kings; Nay, even after their laſt Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> by which they had given them Peace with all the World, beſides many places in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> and <hi>Catalonia</hi> in to boot: Upon which the Poor People promiſed themſelves (though vainly) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n unqueſtionable abatement of Taxes; inſtead of that, they found their Preſſures increaſed daily, and their King, though overgrownly Great and Rich himſelf, yet the People ſo Poor, that thouſands are ſaid to die in a plentiful year, for want of Bread to their Water, nothing being free there, but freſh Water and Air: For (except in ſome few priviledged Places) wherever they have the Conveniency, by their Situation of Sea Water, (leſt they ſhould make uſe of the Benefit of that which God and Nature hath given them, for ſaving the charge of Salt,)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105626:20"/>every Family is forced to take ſo much Salt of the King at his own Rate, (which is above ten times the Price it is ſold for to Strangers for Tranſportation) as is judged they may ſpend in a year; the Lord deliver all other Countries from their Example. In <hi>Sweden,</hi> that King, Court, and their Military Officers, are the better for their Conqueſts in <hi>Germany, Denmark, Ruſſia,</hi> and ſome places anciently belonging to <hi>Poland,</hi> but the Commons the worſe. <hi>Spain</hi> is undone, by the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of People ſent thence to the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> which hath depopulated the Country, <hi>France</hi> reaping more Benefit by keeping their People at home to Manufactures, than <hi>Spain</hi> doth by ſending theirs abroad for Silver and Gold. And now, though by theſe Inſtances it may appear to be the Intereſt of the People of other Nations ſo well as ours, to live in Peace, without coveting Additions; yet it is more our true Intereſt, (becauſe, by reaſon of our Situation, we have no need of Foreign Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier Towns, our Ships well ordered, being better than other Princes bordering Garriſons) than any other Kingdoms, to neglect eſpecially <hi>European</hi> Acquiſition and Colonies, and apply our ſelves,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To the improving of our own Land, of which we have more than we have People to manage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To the Increaſing our Home and Foreign Trades, for which we have natural Advantages above any other Nation.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105626:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly and Laſtly,</hi> (By our Strength which Trade will increaſe) To make uſe of it, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the helps that God and Nature hath given us in our Situation and otherwiſe, in keeping the Ballance amongſt our Neighbours: For if the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> which is but Four hundred thouſand Acres of Profitable Ground, is by the benefit of Trade able to do ſo much, as we experienced the laſt War; what might we do, if Trade were improved, who have much more Advantages for it than they have? I aſcribe what was done by the <hi>Netherlands</hi> in the late War, to the Province of <hi>Holland;</hi> becauſe, that though the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces are Seven in number, <hi>Hollands</hi> due proportion of all Charges, is 58⅓ in a hundred, to all the others 41⅔, of which 41⅔, <hi>Holland</hi> gets little more than 20 honeſtly paid them; inſomuch, that it alone may be reckoned to bear four Fifths in an hundred, to one Fifth that all the other ſix bears: And how Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious a thing is it, that <hi>Holland,</hi> no bigger than as before mentioned, ſhould be able to cope with <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that though their Charges in the late War was abundantly greater than ours, yet by their good Management, to be ſo little the worſe for it, that at the concluſion of the War, to have their Credits ſo high, that they could have commanded what Money they had pleaſed at Three in the Hundred, and all this by the meer additional Benefit of Trade and good Order; and how by <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s indiſcreet neglecting of Trade, and chooſing War when he was in Peace, did he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105626:21"/>miſs the true Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> as by his ill-founded deſigns, he did the Intereſt of the Reformed Religion: For if he had ſucceeded in his unjuſt Invaſion of the Spaniſh Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories in the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt-Indies,</hi> (as God ſeldom proſpereth diſhoneſt Undertakings) it being intended for a State Acquiſition, the Benefit would not have been diffuſive, but chiefly to himſelf and Favourites, and prejudicial to the People in general, though at the Expence of their Subſtance, the Acqueſts would have been made: For had he met with ſo much Succeſs in the gaining thoſe Countries, and in them, that Plenty of Gold and Silver as he vainly hoped for, we ſhould have been as unhappy in them (in the Depopulating of our Countries, by the loſs of the multitude of People that muſt have been ſent thither, and in impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhing our Nations by the vaſt Charge of a continual War) as <hi>Spain</hi> is; and to no other end, than the making of him only Rich, able to Inſlave the remaining People, and to make himſelf Abſolute over them; for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of which, in ſuch Tyrants as <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> ſurely <hi>Moſes</hi> had an Eye, when he ſaid, that they ſhould not greatly multiply Silver and Gold. And thus, as <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s deſigns muſt, to an impartial Judgment, appear to have been laid, ſome Diſhoneſtly, others Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politickly, and all contrary to the Intereſt of the Kingdom; ſo the Iſſue of them was damageable to the People of <hi>England:</hi> As,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> In his ſudden making a Peace with <hi>Holland</hi> ſo ſoon as he got the Government, without thoſe Advantages for Trade, as they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105626:21"/>who beat them did intend to have had, as their Due and juſt Satisfaction for their Charges in the War.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> In his War with <hi>Spain,</hi> by the loſs of that Beneficial Trade to our Nation, and giving it to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> by whoſe hands we drave (during the War) the greateſt part of that Trade which we had of it, with Five and twenty in the Hundred Profit to them, and as much Loſs to us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By our Loſs in that War with <hi>Spain,</hi> of 1500 Engliſh Ships, according as was reported to that Aſſemby, called, <hi>Richard</hi>'s <hi>Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In the Diſgracefulleſt Defeat at <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> that ever this Kingdom ſuffered in any Age or Time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly and Laſtly,</hi> In ſpending the Great Publick Stock he found, and yet leaving a vaſt Debt upon the Kingdom; as appeared by the Accompts brought into <hi>Richard</hi>'s <hi>Aſſembly;</hi> which had (I believe) been yet much higher, but that they who under him managed the Affairs, were a ſort of People who had been long Diſciplin'd (before his time) to a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Frugality, and againſt Cheating; though at Couſening the Poorer People, for their Maſters Benefit, ſome of them were grown as Dexterous, as if they had been bred in the Court of <hi>Spain:</hi> For beſides impoſing <hi>Richard</hi> upon the People, after his Father's Death, by a Forged Title, according to the very Law they took to be in being, when, by his Aſſembly, they were ordered to bring in an Accompt of the Receipts and Payments
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105626:22"/>of the Kingdom; they made about Sixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds ſpent in Intelligence, whereas it coſt not above Three or Four thouſand at moſt; and calculating the reſt by theſe, it may well be concluded, that they were expert in their Trades.</p>
                  <p>It is confeſſed, that <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Peace and League with <hi>France,</hi> was upon Honourable Articles; but as the tottering Affairs of <hi>France</hi> then ſtood, much more could not have been ſooner asked than had; For <hi>Mazerine</hi> being a Man of a large and ſubtle Wit, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the Greatneſs of <hi>England</hi> at that time, which was then dreadful to the World, and the vaſt Advantages <hi>France</hi> would have in pulling down, by their help, of <hi>Spain,</hi> granted him, not only any thing for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that he demanded, but diſregarded alſo, even his Parties making their boaſts of the awe he had him under, conſidering, that when <hi>Cromwell</hi> had helped him, to do his work, in bringing under the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and therein caſting the ballance of Chriſtendom on his ſide, he ſhould afterwards have leiſure to recover what then he ſeemed to part with: And though nothing is more ordinary than to hear Men brag, how <hi>Oliver</hi> vapoured over <hi>France,</hi> I do eſteem <hi>Mazerine</hi>'s complying with him, for his own ends, to be the Chief Piece of all his Miniſtry: For by that means only, and no other, is his Maſter become ſo great at this day, that no Factions at home can diſturb his Peace, nor Powers abroad frighten him; which is more than any King of <hi>France,</hi> ſince <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, could ſay:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105626:22"/>And when his Neighbour Nations have (too late I fear) experienced his Greatneſs, they will find cauſe to Curſe the Ignorance of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Politicks; and therefore, when a true meaſure is taken of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation that he hath in the World, will not be found to have its Foundation in Senſe or Reaſon, but proceeding from Ignorance and Atheiſm: From Ignorance, in thoſe that take all that was done by him, as a Servant, and whilſt under the direction of better Heads than his own, to be done by him alone: And from Atheiſm, in thoſe that think every thing lawful that a Man doth, if it ſucceed to his Advancement. But they that ſhall take an impartial View of his Actions whilſt he was a Single Perſon, and at liberty to make uſe of his own Parts without control, will find nothing worthy Commendations, but cauſe enough from thence to obſerve, that the Wiſdom of his Maſters, and not his own, muſt have been that by which he firſt moved; and to attribute his former Performances, whilſt a Servant, (as is truly due) to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Subtilty of the Long Parliament, under whoſe Conduct and Command he was. And now from <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s neglecting to live in Peace, as if he had pleaſed he might have done with all the World, to the great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of this Nation: The improvement of our Victory over <hi>Holland</hi> in his Peace with them; His being the Cauſe of the loſs of our Spaniſh Trade during all his time; Of the loſs of 1500 Engliſh Ships in that War; beſides, by it, breaking the Ballance of <hi>Europe;</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105626:23"/>Of the Expence of the Publick Stock and Stores he found, with the contracting a Debt of Nineteen hundred thouſand Pounds, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own accompt, (which, for ought I know he left behind him, but am apt to think the Debt was not altogether ſo great, though made ſo to his Son <hi>Richard</hi>'s Aſſembly, as a means to get the more Money from the Poorer People:) And laſtly, Of the diſhonourable overthrow we met with at <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> it may well be concluded, that he laid the Foundation of our preſent want of Trade, to what we formerly enjoyed; and that the reaſon why his Miſcarriages were not ſooner under obſervation, is, becauſe our Stock of Wealth and Honour at his coming to the Government, being then unſpeakably great, ſtifled their appearance, until having ſince had ſome unhappy additional Loſſes, they are now become diſcernable; as firſt Loſſes to a Merchant, who concealedly bears up under them, are afterwards diſcovered by the addition of Second Loſſes that ſink him. When I contemplate theſe great Failings, I cannot but apprehend the ſad Condition any People are in, whoſe Governour drives on a diſtinct contrary Intereſt to theirs; for doubtleſs <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s over-weening Care to ſecure his particular Intereſt, againſt His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty (then abroad) and the Long Parliament, whom he had turned out, with a prodigious Ambition of acquiring a glorious Name in the World, carried him on to all his Miſtakes and Abſurdities, to the irreparable Loſs and Damage of this Famous Kingdom.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:105626:23"/>
                  <p>To prove the Second Aſſertion, That <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Time was full of Oppreſſion and Injuſtice, I ſhall but inſtance in a few of many Particulars, and begin with <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> not that I think him in any kind one that deſerved Favour or Reſpect, but that equal Juſtice is due to the worſt ſo well as beſt Men, and that he comes firſt in order of time.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>John</hi> in 1649. was by Order of the then Parliament tryed for his Life, with an intent (I believe) of taking him away; but the Jury not finding him Guilty, he was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, according to Law, generouſly ſet at Liberty by thoſe that had quarrel enough againſt him. This Example in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of keeping to the Laws in the Caſe of one who was a profeſſed implacable Enemy to them, ought to have been copied by <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well;</hi> but on the contrary, to ſhew that there was a difference betwixt his and his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors (the Long Parliaments) Principles, when the Law had again upon a ſecond Tryal (occaſioned by <hi>Oliver</hi>) cleared <hi>Lilburne,</hi> the Parliaments ſubmitting to the Law was no Example to him; for, contrary to Law, he kept him in Priſon, until he was ſo far ſpent in a Conſumption, that he only turned him out to dye.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Conyes</hi> Caſe is ſo Notorious, that it needs little more than naming: He was a Priſoner at <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Suit, and being brought to the Kings-Bench-Bar by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> had his Counſel taken from the Bar, and ſent to the Tower for no other reaſon, than the pleading of their Clients Cauſe; an
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105626:24"/>Act of Violence, that I believe the whole Story of <hi>England</hi> doth not parallel.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Sir <hi>Henry Vaine,</hi> above any one Perſon, was the Author of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and did ſo long and cordially Eſpouſe his Intereſt, that he prejudiced himſelf (in the opinion of ſome) by it; yet ſo ungrateful was this Monſter of Ingratitude, that he ſtudied to deſtroy him both in Life and Eſtate, becauſe he could not adhere to him in his Perjury and Falſeneſs. The occaſion he took was this, He appointing a publick Day of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and ſeeking of God for him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited all Gods People in his Declaration, to offer him their Advice in the Weighty Affairs then upon his Shoulders: Sir <hi>Henry</hi> taking a Riſe from hence, offered his Advice by a Treatiſe, called, <hi>The Healing Queſtion;</hi> but <hi>Cromwell,</hi> angry at being taken at his word, Seized, Impriſoned, and endeavoured to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further againſt him, for doing only what he had invited him to do; and ſome may think, that Sir <hi>Henry</hi> ſuffered juſtly, for having known him ſo long, and yet would truſt to any thing he ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, In <hi>Richard</hi>'s Aſſembly, certain Priſoners in the Tower, under the then Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and ſome ſent thence to <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and other places beyond the Sea, complained of Falſe Impriſonment. Their Goaler was ſent for, and being required to ſhew by what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he kept thoſe Perſons in hold, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth a Paper all under <hi>Oliver</hi>'s own Hand, as followeth: <hi>Sir, I pray you Seize ſuch and ſuch Perſons, and all others whom you ſhall judge
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105626:24"/>dangerous Men; do it quickly, and you ſhall have a Warrant after you have done.</hi> The nature of this Warrant was by <hi>Richard</hi>'s Aſſembly debated, and having firſt <hi>Richard</hi>'s own Counſel's Opinion in the Caſe, they Voted the Commitment of the Complainants to be Illegal, Unjuſt, and Tyrannical; and that firſt, becauſe the Warrant by which they were Committed, was under the hand of the then (as they called him) Chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, who by Law ought not to commit any by his own Warrant. Secondly, Becauſe no Cauſe was ſhewn in the Warrant. And Thirdly, (In the Caſe of thoſe ſent out of the reach of a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> which in Law is a Baniſhment) Becauſe no Engliſh-man ought to be Baniſhed by any leſs Authority than an Act of Parliament. And therefore, for theſe Reaſons, they Voted farther, that the Priſoners ſhould be ſet at Liberty without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Fees or Charges, but the turning out, and puniſhing the Lieutenant by the Aſſembly (for obeying ſo unjuſt a Warrant) was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by their ſudden Diſſolution.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, The Tyranny in the decimating a Party reſtored to common Priviledges with all others, and the publick Faith given for it, by a Law made to that end, by the then Powers in being, is ſufficiently ſhewed in the mentioning of it, only there is this aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating Circumſtance in it, That <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who was the principal Perſon in procuring that Law, when he thought it for his Advantage not to keep it, was the only Man for breaking it: But to the Honour of his firſt Aſſembly, next
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105626:25"/>following, it may be remembred, that they no ſooner came together, than like true Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are always jealous of the Rights and Priviledges of the People, damned the Act of Decimation, as an unjuſt and wicked breach of Faith.</p>
                  <p>The third Aſſertion of <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s knowing no Honeſty, where he thought his particular Intereſt was concerned, is made good: Firſt, (though therein he miſtook his Intereſt) in his odious and unjuſt War with <hi>Spain,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt provocations, meerly out of an ambitious and covetous deſign of robbing that Prince of his Silver and Gold Mines, and becauſe he judged it for his Credit to diſguiſe his unlawful deſires, he proceeded in it, by imploying his Creatures in the City, to draw the Merchants to complain of Injuries done them by <hi>Spain,</hi> and to Petition for Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but by a croſs Providence, his Project had a contrary Succeſs; for inſtead of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerin, his Seekings, the Merchants remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to him, the great prejudice that a War with <hi>Spain</hi> would be to <hi>England;</hi> and ſhewed, that that King had been ſo far from Injuring us, that he had done more for Compliance and preventing a breach with <hi>England,</hi> than ever he had done in favour of any other Nation. But when <hi>Oliver</hi> ſaw his Method would not take, he called the Remonſtrators Malignants, and begun the War of his own accord, in which he was highly ingrateful in deſigning the ruine of that Prince, who all along had been moſt Faithful to his Party.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105626:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> His Falſeneſs and Ingratitude ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared Superlatively in turning out his Maſters, who had not only advanced him, but made themſelves the more odious by their partial Affection towards him, and in his doing it, with the breach of a Poſitive Negative Oath, taken once a year, when made a Counſellor of State, beſides the breach of all other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, Voluntary Imprecations, Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Oaths, taken frequently upon all occaſions in Diſcourſe and Declarations; and yet further (when he had turned them out) and left them void of Protection, and expoſed them to the Fury of the People, in purſuing them with falſe reproachful Declarations, enough to have ſtirred up the rude multitude to have deſtroyed them, wherever they had met them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> His want of Honour, ſo well as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, appeareth yet further, in that having, by a long Series of a ſeeming pious Deportment, gained, by his Diſſimulation, good thoughts in his Maſters, the Long Parliament, and by his Spiritual Gifts, winded himſelf into ſo good an opinion with the Soldiers, (Men generally of plain Breeding, that knew little beſides their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Trade, and Religious Exerciſes) that he could impoſe, in Matters of Buſineſs, what Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief he pleaſed upon them; he made uſe of the Credit he had with each, to abuſe both, by many vile Practices for making himſelf Popular, &amp; the Parliament and Army odious to one another; and becauſe the Artifices he uſed are too many to enumerate, I ſhall but inſtance in ſome few; As his ſly complaining Inſinuations againſt the Army to the Parliament, and againſt them to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105626:26"/>the Army: His being the chief Cauſe of the Parliaments giving Rewards to his Creatures, and then whiſpering Complaints amongſt his Officers of their ill Husbandry. His obſtructing the Houſe in their buſineſs, by long drawling Speeches, and other ways, and then complaining of them to his Soldiers, that he could not get them to do any thing that was good: His giving fair words to every one, without keeping pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with any, except for his own Advantage, &amp; then excuſing all with Forgetfulneſs: And his deſerting his Major Generals in their Decima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, crying out moſt againſt them himſelf, when he only had ſet them at work, becauſe queſtioned by his Aſſembly, is not to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would not be underſtood to remember any thing here, in Favour of the Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for what might be Wicked in him, might be Juſt as to them; And though, if what he did, had been for the Reſtauration of his Majeſty, he might have been excuſed, yet being for his own Single Advancement, it is unpardonable, and leaves him a Perſon to be truly admired for nothing but Apoſtaſie and Ambition, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Tiberius</hi> in Diſſimulation. I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that ſome think it matter of praiſe in him, that he kept us in Peace Four years and nine months; but that hath little in it, his Majeſty having done the like, almoſt double his time, ſince his Return, with one fifth part of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Soldiers which he commanded; though he hath alſo had the trouble of preſſing, and ſometimes forcing Uniformity in Religion, which he found under ſeveral Forms; whereas <hi>Oliver</hi> kept the Nation purpoſely divided in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105626:26"/>Opinions, and himſelf of no declared Judgment, as the ſecureſt way of ingaging all ſeveral Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions equally to him; which Artifice, together with his leaving the Church Lands alienated as he found them, were all the true Principles of Policy that I know of, which he kept unto. The Honeſty of theſe Principles, I refer to the judgment of every Man's Conſcience; but if we may judge of things by Experience and Succeſs, they ſeem to have been very happy in the World; For in comparing the Condition of the Proteſtant Countries at preſent, to what they were in times of Popery, we ſhall find them abundantly more conſiderable now than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; for in taking a true Survey of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Dominions, we ſhall diſcover them to bear no proportion at all in largeneſs, to the Popiſh, and that there is nothing that keeps the Ballance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Parties, but the Advantage that the firſt hath, in being free from the Bondage of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the latters being under it; For as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Mercies are (by their Principles) Cruelties, ſo had they power anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the natural Richneſs of the Soil of their Countries, and extent of their Territories, they would long e're this have ſwallowed up the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches, and made Bonfires of their Members; but as God, in his Mercy and Wiſdom, hath by his Over-ruling Hand of Providence, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved his Church; ſo for the Romiſh Churches Inability to effect that which they have Will and Malice enough to carry them on to do, there are theſe natural Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> There being generally of the Popiſh Countries, above one Moyety belonging to Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Monks, Fryars and Nuns, who, like Droans,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105626:27"/>ſpend the Fat of the Land, without contributing any thing to the good of Mankind, renders them much the leſs conſiderable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Marriage being forbidden to all theſe Sorts and Orders, occaſions great want of People every where, (they being uncapable of any Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren but thoſe of Darkneſs) except in <hi>France,</hi> which is an extraordinary Caſe, proceeding partly by not being ſo ſubject to <hi>Rome,</hi> as other Countries of that belief are; but eſpecially from the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Proteſtants that are among them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The blind Devotion of theſe People, carrying them on to vaſt Expences, in the Building and richly adorning of many needleſs and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Churches, Chapels and Croſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the making chargeable Preſents by the better, and Pilgrimages by the meaner ſort, to their Idols, keeps all degrees under.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The many Holidays, upon which the labouring Man is forbidden to work, adds much to their Poverty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But Fifthly and Laſtly,</hi> The vaſt number of Being Friars, who living Idly, and purely upon the Sweat of other Mens Brows, without taking any labour themſelves, makes it impoſſible for the lower ſort of People, who think they are bound in Conſcience to relieve them, ever to get above a mean Condition. Now whoſoever ſhall ſeriouſly weigh and ponder theſe Circumſtances, under which the Popiſh Countries lye, and conſider the Reformeds Advantage in being free from them, muſt confeſs it the leſs wonder, that the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Princes and States, with their ſmall Dominions, compared to the others Great, are able to bear up againſt them; and now as the Alienation of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105626:27"/>Church-lands, the turning out the Romiſh Vermin, the Prieſts, Monks, Friars and Nuns, (who devour all Countries wherever they come) and freedom from the Popiſh Impoſition upon Conſcience, hath mightily increaſed the Greatneſs of the Proteſtant Princes and States, to what they antiently were, and the not doing the ſame in the Popiſh Countries, keeps thoſe Princes under; ſo, even amongſt the Reformed, where the Church-lands are moſt alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and Liberty of Conſcience moſt given, they proſper moſt, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> and ſome parts of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> with other places. And I dare undertake to be a Prophet in this, That if ever any Proteſtant Country ſhould be ſo far forſaken of the Lord, as to be ſuffered to turn unto Popery, theſe Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will be made good in their viſible loſs of the Splendor, Riches, Power and Greatneſs, that they now know.</p>
                  <p>Had <hi>Cromwell</hi> been a Perſon of an open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Life, his Actions had been leſs Scandalous; but having been a Profeſſor of Religion, they are not to be pleaded for; neither can it be conſiſtent with Religion, to palliate them which have been of ſo much offence, and (as may be feared) made ſo many Atheiſts in the World: And I cannot but ſtand amazed, when I hear him extolled by ſome, not ignorant of his Practices, knowing in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and (as I hope) fearing God.</p>
                  <p>Now I will ſuppoſe, I may be ſuſpected to have been injured or diſobliged by <hi>Oliver;</hi> but I can with Truth affirm, I never received either Good or Evil from him in all my Life, more than in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the whole Kingdom (which I think may be allowed to render me the more a Competent Judge in his Caſe,) and that I am ſo far from being
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105626:28"/>moved unto this, out of any quarrel to him, that, as I have here mentioned, ſome few of many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtices and State-errors, that he was guilty of in his ſhort time, if I were conſcious of any thing more, during his Protectorſhip, worthy applauſe, than I have here mentioned, I ſhould not envy it him, but freely remember it; and if any think I have not ſaid enough on his behalf, and too much to his diſadvantage, I have this for my Buckler, that I wiſh I could have ſaid more for him, and had known leſs againſt him; profeſſing, that beſides what I have here hinted, I am wholly ignorant of any one Action in all his Four years and nine months time, done either Wiſely, Vertuouſſy, or for the Intereſt of this Kingdom; and therefore that I am none of his Admirers, I ought to be pardoned by my Readers.</p>
                  <p>Much more might be ſaid upon this Subject, but this may ſuffice to ſhew, that if <hi>Mazerine</hi> (at the hearing of <hi>Oliver</hi>'s death) thought he had then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for calling him a Fortunate Fool, if he were now living he would find more Cauſe for it, <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>'s Lot, as to Reputation, having been exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly much greater ſince his Death, than whilſt he was in the World: And that from forgetfulneſs of his Impolitick Government, (from whoſe Entrance we may date the Commencement of our Trades decay,) And (through want of Memory) in Mens giving to him the Cauſe of our former Wealth and Proſperity, which truly belonged to others. But what Opinion ſoever <hi>Mazerine</hi> may have had of <hi>Oliver,</hi> he was without all peradventure a Perſon of more than ordinary Wit, and no otherwiſe a Fool than as he wanted Honeſty, no Man being wiſe but an Honeſt Man.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
